<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence and vindication of the right of tithes, against sundry late scandalous pamphlets: shewing, the lawfullnesse of them, and the just remedy in law for them, as well in London as elsewhere. / Penned by a friend to the Church of England, and a lover of truth and peace.</title>
            <author>A Friend to the Church of England, and a Lover of Truth and Peace.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E339_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859428</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111508</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81692)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111508)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E339[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence and vindication of the right of tithes, against sundry late scandalous pamphlets: shewing, the lawfullnesse of them, and the just remedy in law for them, as well in London as elsewhere. / Penned by a friend to the Church of England, and a lover of truth and peace.</title>
                  <author>A Friend to the Church of England, and a Lover of Truth and Peace.</author>
                  <author>Downame, John, d. 1652,</author>
                  <author>Nomophilos Philotolis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller, dwelling in the Black-Friers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Incorrectly attributed to John Downame, whose imprimatur on page [8] has been mistaken for the signature to the dedicatory epistle, which is in fact signed in Greek characters at the foot of page [7]: Nomophilos Philotolis.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 30th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111508:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111508:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE AND VINDICATION of the Right of TITHES, Againſt ſundry late ſcandalous Pamphlets: <hi>SHEWING,</hi> The lawfullneſſe of them, and the juſt Remedy in Law for them, as well in <hi>London</hi> as elſewhere.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAL. 3.8.</hi>
               </bibl> Will a man rob God? yet ye have robbed me: but ye ſay, Wherein have we robbed thee? in Tithes and offerings.</q>
            <p>Penned by a Friend to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and a lover of Truth and Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Miller,</hi> dwelling in the <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111508:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111508:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THOMAS ADAMS, Lord Major of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſtoried of <hi>Diogenes</hi> (a wiſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, though a ſullen Cynick) that when he was about to dis, he deſired his friends about him to bury him after his death with his face downward; they thinking this requeſt to proceed rather from his humour then from his wiſedom, demanded of him the reaſon; he told them, <hi>That very ſhortly the world would be turned upſide down, and then his face would lie upward:</hi> I need not apply this ſtory, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is no ſtranger in this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and cannot but
<pb facs="tcp:111508:3"/>obſerve this manner of Change, you now ſitting at the Helm for the government of this goodly City, I had almoſt ſaid Nation (for <hi>England</hi> is in <hi>London</hi> at this day.)</p>
            <p>I will not ſpeak of that lovely Gemini, Religion and Law, which in the judgement of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Religio eſt ibi bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; bona diſciplina, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sublata vera R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligione cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ere Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt: Quta ſublato timore Dei ſequ tur impietas, &amp; ex ca ruina Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum. <hi>Mach.</hi> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Dec. <hi>l. iv.</hi> c. <hi>11. Pſal. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Machiavell</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf do riſe and fall together: I will only call upon your Lordſhip with the Prophet, to come and behold the works of the Lord, what alterations he hath made in this great City of <hi>London;</hi> which I have ſometimes known, as a City like <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at unity within it ſelf: not a convicted Recuſant, nor a notorious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike or Schiſmatick to be found within the walls of that City. <hi>London,</hi> whoſe twelve Companies, like the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were wont to go up by multitudes to the Houſe of God, not in the ſound of a Trumpet and Alarm of warre, but with the joifull voices of Peace and Praiſe, like thoſe that kept holy day. <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Lord Majors ſword was almoſt as formidable within that City, as the Scepter without. But is <hi>London</hi> ſo now? I will ſay no more, but weep out the reſt for that City where I was born and bred, and where I have ſpent moſt of my daies; whoſe proſperity and wellfare I have ever ſought,<note place="margin">Quae peccatis perijt, ſtetibus ſtetit. <hi>Jer.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt al <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ium.</hi>
               </note> and ſhall daily pray for, in the ſenſe of <hi>Ierome</hi> concerning <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> that what ſin had thrown down from the firmeneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:111508:3"/>of rocks, grace might re-establiſh in the ſoftneſſe of tears.</p>
            <p>The ſubject of this enſuing diſcourſe (being in the number of thoſe things that are turned upſide down) is no ſtranger to your Lordſhip (though the Authour be) and cranes your patronage which in juſtice you cannot tell how to deny, your Lordſhip being appointed by the Law of the Land the ſole Chancellour and Iudge of Tithes in <hi>London</hi> (a felicity beyond all the Kingdom beſides, where the Law is at this day ſomewhat looſe and unſetled, but only in London.)</p>
            <p>Fourteen yeers are not yet elapſed and gone, ſince it was a common Question among the Divines of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> not whether Tithes were due, but whether they were not due <hi>jure divino.</hi> Since it was accounted a moſt pious and religious worke, in divers of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips predeceſſours, to be appointed Truſtees for the buying in of Impropriations of Tithes, and reſtoring them to the Church. Since conſciencious men could not die peaceably in their beds, till they had made reſtitution of ſubſtracted Tithes. But now of late, a ſtrange New-light hath appeared to a generation of men, diſpleaſed with old Truths; not ſuch a light as appeared to the Wiſe-men leading them to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.11.</note> and preſenting him with their gold, frankincenſe and myrrhe, but ſuch a kinde of light as appeared to the ſouldiers, by which
<pb facs="tcp:111508:4"/>they took our Saviour in the night, and ſtript him of all he had:<note place="margin">Joh. 18 3.</note> Theſe men in their Petitions to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, confidently tell you (for they ſeldom ſpeak mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destly) that Tithes are Popiſh, yea Iewiſh, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to he aboliſhed; the endowment of Churches by them, ſuperſtitious; the withholding of them, lawfull; and the paiment of them, injurious. Whether Will not this ſpirit of errour (in the appearance of an Angel of light) at laſt lead them? nay, unto what height hath it not already carried them, when they can turn Beaſt into <hi>Beſt,</hi> and plead for a very <hi>Saul</hi> to be a true <hi>Paul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, Fame hath reported you to be a Iudge of the old Portraiture, To have an Eagles eye, by an exact and diligent ſearch into the Cauſe before you; a Ladies hand in the tranſaction of Cauſes with much tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and compaſſion; and a Lions heart, to break the jaws of the wicked, and to pluck the prey out of their teeth.</p>
            <p>God and the Law, by diners ancient and late Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which the Kings and Princes of this Nation, in their grace and favour have granted to the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> (which they made and called their <hi>Chamber</hi>) have armed your Lordſhip with <hi>Power</hi> to do great things: if you exerciſe it with your <hi>Parts,</hi> no Gariſons ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>ſchiſme</hi> or <hi>ſinne,</hi> can long hold out in this City.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:111508:4"/>In this great accompliſhment I need not prompt your Lordſhip what to do, I doubt not but you will make it <hi>your ſtudy, your care, your duty,</hi> to purge this City from that accurſed and execrable ſinne of Sacriledge, by cauſing the maws of ſuch guilty perſons (like the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Ionahs</hi> whale) to diſgorge the law full patrimony of the Church; that the bleſsing of him that was ready to periſh, may come upon you, and that you may cauſe the hearts of the poor Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> to ſing for joy; that your daies may be multiplied as the ſand, and when they expire, that God may then make you to die in your neſt, leaving a bleſſed memorial behinde you.</p>
            <p>It was the praiſe of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, to be called the Advocate of Gods Church, which be thought a greater glory to him, then to be Emperour of the whole world. And let it be a greater Honour to the great Lord Major of <hi>London</hi> (for ſo hath bis Office made him) to be accounted the Churches Advocate, in help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> to their juſt Patrimony, then to be Governour in Chief of that great City; which Honour, let it be the portion and inheritance of your Lordſhip, and of your vertuous Succeſſours for ever; So prayeth he that maketh it his utmoſt ambition, to be to your Lordſhip and to that whole City, an</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Avowed obliged ſervant, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:111508:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <date>May the <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1646.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111508:5"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF TITHES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE common Law of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">K. <hi>Iames</hi> Parl. Speech, 1609.</note> the beſt Law for this Nation in the world (as might eaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ily be proved, were it incident to the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I have in hand) doth lay forth all it's intereſt and juriſdiction in the preſervation and maintenance of three things, <hi>The juſt priviledges and preeminences of the Crowne of England, The juſt rights of the Church of England, And the juſt rights and liberties of the people of England.</hi> The firſt is called by the Regiſter of Writs, <hi>Pririlegium Regis,</hi> or <hi>Jus Regium.</hi> The ſecond is called, <hi>Jus Eccleſiae,</hi> or <hi>Jus Ecclepaſiasticum.</hi> The third is called, <hi>Jus Populi,</hi> or <hi>Libertates Angliae.</hi> Theſe three make up the whole body of the common Law, a Law ſo peaceable for the keeping all theſe three in unity, that for this very cauſe it is, by the ancient Laws of this Realm, ſtiled by the name of Peace; <hi>Pax Dei,</hi> in reference to the rights of the Church, <hi>Pax Regis,</hi> in reference to the rights of the King, and <hi>Pax Regni,</hi> in reference to the rights of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111508:6"/>people. I ſhall write only of the firſt, and but of ſome part of that neither, <hi>viz.</hi> concerning the endowments of the Church with Glebe and Tithes, by occaſion of divers late ſcandalous Pamphlets, or rather Paſquils, calling them Jewiſh, Popiſh, Antichriſtian, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſcarce fit to be named, leſſe fit to be anſwered with any other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, then that of <hi>Seneca, Solocontemptu reſpondere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that reproveth a ſcorner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pror. 9.</note> ſaith <hi>Solomon, getteth himſelf a blot,</hi> which falleth out eſpecially where a man is to deal with the Vulgar, more fitted to quarrell then to judge, and much apter to wrangle, then to reſolve, whoſe diſcourſes when you ſhall have rak'd into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the very bottom, you ſhall finde more ſlanders of truth then objections againſt it, and ſcandals in ſtead of arguments. And to ſtrive with ſuch kinde of men, whoſe contention is more for victory, then for truth, the match is not equall; which hath made me often to pity the lot of many learned men in theſe days, who for their religious and painfull writings againſt <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries,</hi> have received no other rewards of their labours then thoſe that meddle with waſps. And therefore I will at preſent anſwer all their erroneous papers concerning Tithes, <hi>oſtendendo veritatem,</hi> by holding forth the truth to all that will ſee it, the light whereof, if it appear not to them, it is becauſe their mindes are either darkned through ignorance, or obſtinated with errour; like thoſe men who in a clear Sun-ſhine ſee no light, becauſe they are either na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally blinde, or wilfully cloſe their eyes. <hi>Veritas</hi> (ſaith the Philoſopher) <hi>eſt index ſui &amp; obliqui.</hi> I ſhall therefore in this ſhort diſcourſe handle only two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That Tithes are juſtly and lawfully due to Miniſters under the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>2 .That thoſe Miniſters have a juſt remedy in Law to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover them in all places, and particularly in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111508:6"/>For the opening and underſtanding of the firſt, it would not be impertinent to handle four things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The originall of Tithes.</item>
               <item>2. By whom, and to whom they ought to be paid.</item>
               <item>3. Out of what things they are to be paid. And</item>
               <item>4. By what right Tithes are due: wherein there is a great controverſie and a large diſpute between the School-men, the Canoniſts, the Civilians and Caſuiſts, whether Tithes be due <hi>jure Divino,</hi> or <hi>jure Canonice, or jure Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio,</hi> or <hi>jure mixto.</hi> But I intend a ſhort diſcourſe, and not a volume. All theſe things are handled at large in <hi>Summa Roſella,</hi> and <hi>Summa Angelica,</hi> in <hi>Azorius, Navarra, Rebuffus, Linwood,</hi> and others; and therefore. I ſhall paſſe them over, all of them agreeing in this, that Tithes are rightfully due to Church-men, and the detenſion of them is no leſſe crime then ſacriledge. I will only apply my ſelf to ſhew by what right the endowment of Churches by Tithes and Glebe are due here in <hi>England,</hi> a Nation that exceeds any in the world for liberality and bounty to Clergy-men (which is an ancient and very proper name for Miniſters of the Goſpel ordained to that function, as I ſhall ſhew anon.)</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the clearing of which I ſhall lay down theſe grounds.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That in all ages of the world, as well in the time of the Goſpel, as in the time of the Law, holy and devout men, not out of ſuperſtition or blinde zeal, but out of conſcience and honour to Almighty God, whom they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and in duty to him the ſupream Lord of their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſtance, as well as of their ſouls and bodies, have ever given and beſtowed upon him and his ſervice, as a free gift, ſome part and portion of their goods and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. And the firſt that in the book of God we finde to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111508:7"/>have offered in this kinde, were two of the holieſt men that ever trod upon Gods earth, <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> the one the father of all the faithfull; the other of all the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and that which they both pitcht upon in their gifts, were Tithes. <hi>For Abaham,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>gave to Melchiſedech Prieſt of the high God Tithe of all,</hi> Gen. 14.20. and <hi>Jacob</hi> in his journey to <hi>Haran</hi> vowed a vow to God, that if he would be with him, and bleſſe him in that journey, <hi>Of all that thou ſhalt give</hi> (ſaid he, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22.) <hi>I will ſurely give the Tenth unto thee.</hi> Whether theſe two Patriarks did this by inſtinct of nature (the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, according to <hi>Pliny</hi> in his <hi>Nat. hiſt. lib.</hi> 12. doing the like) or whether by a divine compariſon they thought it not as fit a proportion to give to God a tenth of their goods, as a ſeventh of their time; or whether there being at that time no law written, nor Prophet to inſtruct them, they were not taught of God ſo to doe (with whom they had familiarity by his frequent apparitions to them) and as a proportion which he afterwards would require and command to be given to <hi>Levi,</hi> one of their children, and to his poſterity, out of which he choſe the Prieſthood, I will not now diſpute it. After this, they and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity built Altars and Tabernacles to God, and <hi>Solomon</hi> built him a ſumptuous Temple, the glory of the world, and the infinite riches that were given to theſe in Cedars, Shittim wood, marble, braſſe, iron, ſilver, gold, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are invaluable. In the time of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and at ſuch time as the Church was in perſecution, as in the times of the Apoſtles (all of them ſuffering mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, ſaith <hi>Dorotheus,</hi> but <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt) the firſt Chriſtians ſold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all their poſſeſſions, and gave the price of them to God, laying them down at the Apoſtles feet, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. And ſince the daies of perſecution, when
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111508:7"/>the Church of God had reſt and peace, thoſe moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> what by the Churches and Temples they built and dedicated to God, the large and liberal endowments of them with Glebe and Tithes, the honour and reſpect they gave to Church-men, the ſtrict Lawes they made for the quiet enjoyment of thoſe endowments, and againſt the alienation of them from the Church, have rendered them famous for piety and vertue to all poſterity. And here in <hi>England,</hi> about an hundred years before, <hi>Lucius</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King; and firſt anointed in the world, and divers more Kings of <hi>England,</hi> long before the daies of ſuperſtition (which I will not meddle with, abhorring ſuperſtition as much as any) followed the ſame patern, and the firſt words of their Charters and grants, began like that of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mag Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ch. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Conceſsimus Deo &amp; Eccleſiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond ground is this, That the Law of God penned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> concerning the paiment of Tithes to the Levites, from whom were the Prieſthood, as to the letter of that Law, as it refers to a preciſe tenth part of the fruits of the earth, neither more nor leſſe, and the manner of the paiment of it, in relation to the ſacrifices of the old Law, is meerly Ceremoniall, and abrogated by Chriſt, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a living Sacrifice, put an end to theſe dead ones under <hi>Moſes;</hi> but as to the equity of Tithes, that a competent portion (I doe not ſay, <hi>quota pars,</hi> a juſt tenth, but <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta pars,</hi> a fit maintenance) ſhould out of the fruits of the earth be allowed for the livelihood and ſupport of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall Prieſthood under Chriſt, which came in lieu of the Leviticall Prieſthood under <hi>Moſes,</hi> it is morall and laſts to this day. This I prove by the Law it ſelf, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Behold, I have given the children of Levi all the tenth in Iſrael for an inheritance, for their ſervice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111508:8"/>ſerve, even the ſervice of the Tabernacle of the Congregation.</hi> This was the reaſon of that Law, now that kinde of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood being changed, and a better come in the room, and ſuch who ſerve at a better Tabernacle, and at a better Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, being Chriſt himſelf (for ſo he is called, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10.) and who offers a better Sacrifice to God then the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prieſthood, even a Sacrifice of praiſe to God continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, as the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. It is great reaſon that theſe, performing the ſame ſervice in ſubſtance, ſhould partake of the ſame, or like wages. This is the very Argument of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Do not you know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that they which minister about holy things, live of the things of the Temple, and they which wait at the Altar are partakers of the Altar? even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that thoſe which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> This will better appear by comparing the Law of Tithes with other things under the Law, which are now abrogated by the Goſpel as to the Ceremony, but as to the ſubſtance and morality remain to this day. I will, in ſtead of many, give but two or three inſtances.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Law of the Sabbath by the fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tied men to the obſervation of a ſeventh day, which ſeventh day the Jews obſerved from the firſt day of the Creation, this, as to that day, is now as much abrogated as the paiment of Tithes to the Levites; there is no precept in all the new Teſtament for altering of that day to the firſt day of the week, but only the conſtant cuſtome of the Church, ever ſince the time of Chriſt. Is therefore the morality of the Sabbath gone? God forbid. Here might I take occaſion to commend the Church of <hi>England</hi> above any reformed Church in the world, for the holy obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this day; but I will not digreſſe. And therefore, I ſay, as the morality of the Sabbath ſtill continues, as to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111508:8"/>give God one day in ſeven for his worſhip, ſo, I ſay, the morality of the Law of Tithes, as to a fit maintenance for Gods Miniſters that attend the worſhip, continues to this day in <hi>England,</hi> and I hope ever will.</item>
               <item>2. The Law of Circumciſion, as to the cutting off of the fore-skin of the fleſh in Infants, is meerly Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; but yet the morality of it, as to baptizing of Infants, ſtill continues, and yet there is no precept in the Goſpel for baptizing of Infants.</item>
               <item>3. The like inſtance is in the Paſchall Lamb, abrogated as to that Ceremony, but ſtill continues, as to the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper, which comes in the room there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; from both which may be concluded ſtrong inferences of reaſon for the continuance of Tithes in that ſenſe I have expreſſed of them.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3. The third ground is this, that this way of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Church-men by Tithes, is the moſt ancient, and the moſt juſt way that can be named.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, it is as old as <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> Prieſt to the Ancient of daies, and from the time of the Law; and all the time of Chriſtianity, it hath continued a conſtant Church-maintenance thorowout Chriſtendome, till the Reformation of Religion in the daies of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi> In thoſe places of reformed Religion, where the Reformation was orderly, which are farre the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that kinde of maintenance continues to this day. But where it was done by popular tumult and power of the Sword, that kinde of maintenance was taken away, and with it the very Churches themſelves, and the moſt part of their revenues.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, It is moſt juſt. There were three principle reaſons why Tithes were to be paid to the Levites of the Law. The firſt, in reſpect of their perſons. The ſecond,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111508:9"/>in regard of their work. And the third, in regard of their wages.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, The Law is given in <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.20. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.9. that <hi>Levi</hi> was not to have any inheritance in the Land, like the other Tribes; for that God was his part and inheritance, and they were his, and that they ſhould wholly depend upon him, not upon the gifts of men; which he ſhewed, in that he gave them their maintenance by the encreaſe of the fruits of the earth, being an act of his immediate providence, all the men in the world being not able to make the ſmalleſt herb of the field to grow. And is not this the caſe of <hi>Levi</hi> under the Goſpel? Are not the Miniſters under the Goſpel truly, and properly, and very anciently called, <hi>Clerus Domini,</hi> the Lords portion or inheritance, for theſe two reaſons? Firſt, As the <hi>Levites</hi> were ſeparated from the reſt of the Tribes for the Lords Sanctuary: So are Miniſters under the Goſpel ſeparated from all the people by Ordination from God in impoſition of hands. The Text for this is very plain, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. For when at the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> certain Prophets and teachers were met; amongſt whom was <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> (afterward called <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>As theſe miniſtred to the Lord and faſted, the holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them,</hi> &amp;c. Here is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſenſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Gods lot or inheritance, in that they are ſeparated by the holy Ghoſt to God, and to his ſervice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Tithes which the Levites received out of the fruits of the earth were called Gods portion: ſo are the Tithes paid to Church-men under the Goſpel, frequently called Gods portion, or <hi>patrimonium Eccleſiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond reaſon why Tithes were paid to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, was for their work and continuall attendance at his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111508:9"/>Altar, for they were either praying or ſacrificing, or preparing for the ſacrifice all the day long, and therefore they were not to be troubled with plowing and ſowing, and other labours that ſhould hinder them from the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary. And doth not the ſame reaſon hold for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters under the Goſpel? are they not in the work of the Miniſtery, to be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon. The ancient Fathers in the Primitive times (I will not ſay it is ſo now) were either praying or preaching, or writing, or ſtudying, all the dayes of their lives, and medled not with ſecular buſineſſes; And this is the reaſon why by the Statute of 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. chap. 13. Miniſters are not to take Lands to farm, under the pain of ten Pounds a Moneth, that they might not be diſtracted in their Miniſteriall function, in preaching and teaching Gods Word, as it is expreſt in that Statute: and this is the cauſe why the maintenance by Tithes was provided for them, as having the leaſt diſtraction in it. A man may take Tithes (as the Engliſh proverb is, in his ſhirt) The meaning is, there is no plowing, nor ſowing, nor mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the gathering up of Tithes: nor any ſuch toylſom labour, as to wear out his old cloaths, nor at ſuch a time of the year, as to put him to the charge to buy new.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third reaſon is in reſpect of their wages, as their perſons were to be holy, ſo their wages were to be juſt. The hire of a whore, and the price of a dog, was not to be brought into the houſe of the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. If the payments had been made to them, or to Miniſters now, in ſummes of money, they might have been the wages of bribery, extortion and oppreſſion: But their wages were to ariſe out of the innocent and harmles fruits of the earth, whoſe naturall productions are not guilty of any manner of bribery or corruption.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111508:10"/>4. My fourth and laſt ground is this; Admitting there were no Law of nature to warrant that duty, of giving part of our goods and poſſeſſions to God and his Church, nor no ground in Scripture to warrant that Law, yet when ſuch things are by ſolemne and deliberate Acts of men, and ſometimes by inſtruments under their hands and ſeals given to God, they remain the proper poſſeſſion of God to the worlds end, and cannot be alienated, nor taken away from that pious uſe to which they were given; if they be, God accounts it as a robbery done to him. When things are given to God and his ſervice, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of thoſe things are in God, and ſo he accounts of them: When <hi>Solomon</hi> built him a Temple, and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to his worſhip, God calls it his; <hi>My houſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall be called the houſe of prayer.</hi> And as God thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of the things given to him, ſo was it the intent and meaning of all thoſe that honoured him with theſe gifts to inveſt him with the whole property and intereſt of them: In which reſpect the ſtile of ancient Graunts and Charters runne according to that of <hi>Mag. Charta.</hi> cap. 1. <hi>We have given to God, for us and our heirs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We know</hi> ſaith Charles the great,<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>Car.</hi> lib. 6.</note> 
               <hi>that the goods of the Church, are the ſacred indowments of God. To the Lord our God we offer and dedicate whatſoever we deliver to his Church:</hi> And the taking away of ſuch things from the uſe they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, hath been in all ages, and by all Lawes accounted Sacriledge.</p>
            <p>And ſo was the Law of Nations, as appears by that Law of the 12. Tables, <hi>Sacrum ſacrove commendatum qui d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpſerit rapſeritve paricida esto:</hi> He that ſhall take away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſacred thing, or that is given to a ſacred uſe, let him be accounted a Parricide; And we know that <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Saphirah</hi> were for this cauſe ſmitten with death, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111508:10"/>the reaſon was given, becauſe that after they had given the ownerſhip to God, the price of their Lands was not their own. And who ever ſhall but read the ſolemn execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, uſed in thoſe ancient Charters of Church-endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, againſt thoſe that ſhall alienate them to other uſes: a man would wonder, how any man durſt preſume to fetch but a ſtick from that Altar to kindle his own fire; leſt it ſhould utterly waſte and conſume his habitation for ever.</p>
            <p>We may obſerve by daily experience, in the ordinary caſes of Charitable uſes, upon the Statute of 43 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 4. When Lands or goods are given by men for the mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a High-way, or the repairing of a Bridge, if the Truſtees for this charitable uſe, ſhall turn this gift to their own private profit, it is in Law a miſimployment, contrary to the intention of the donour, for which they forfeit their truſt, and other men ſhall by the Commiſſioners be put in their rooms, and their eſtates ſhall be anſwerable for that miſimployment: Nay if they beſtow this gift upon a more pious uſe, as the repair of a Church, the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a Preacher. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet this is a miſimployment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not according to the minde of the donour, whoſe intention is in this caſe of ſuch eſteem in Law, that all Decrees made by Commiſſioners upon that Statute, if they be againſt the apparant intention of the donour are void, whoſe intention is ſo reſpected in Law, that rather then it ſhall not be performed, the fundamentall rules of Law ſhall not be obſerved: as to give one example in ſtead of many. By the rule of Law, Copy hold Land cannot be aliend but by ſurrender, but yet if. a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe Land, not formerly ſurrendred to a charitable uſe,<note place="margin">15 <hi>Iac. Rivers</hi> Caſe in Cane.</note> yet this is good, and ſhall be conſtrued an appointment to a Charitable uſe within the Statute of 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Eliz.</hi> though
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111508:11"/>by the rules of Law it could not paſſe without ſurrender. How much more is the Law of <hi>England</hi> carefull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the endowments of the Church, given to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt uſes, wherein the founders are ſo carefull to preſerve them in the continuance of thoſe uſes, that you ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly finde in the end of their Charters of grant, words to this effect; <hi>If any ſhall take away, or apply to any other uſe, that which I have here given, let him be Anathema, and let his account be without mercy at the dreadfull day of judgement, when he ſhall receive his doom from the Judge of Heaven and earth, to whom I dedicate the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I done with my Grounds, in all which, as likewiſe throughout my whole diſcourſe, I deſire to be only underſtood concerning Tithes and Glebe, being the only ſubject matter of this Treatiſe, and the only things now oppoſed by thoſe Pamphlets.</p>
            <p>Theſe four grounds being laid, it will now be no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult matter to prove the firſt head I laid down, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Tythes are juſtly and lawfully due to Miniſters under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are due to them by the Law of the Goſpel, that Law which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Ordinance of God, in theſe words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordeigned, that thoſe which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel:</hi> The reaſon of this Law is rendred in the verſe next before, <hi>Do ye not know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thoſe which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple, and they which wait at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar; Even ſo hath the Lord ordeigned, that thoſe which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> So that the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Law of the Goſpel agree both in this, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel are to have as due to them, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable maintenance with the Levites and Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111508:11"/>the Law: The Levites that miniſtred about holy things, they were to have of the Tithes belonging to the Temple, but were no offering of the Altar: The Prieſts that attended at the Altar, were to have as their due from the people (for ſo is the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.3.) of every ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice offered on the Altar, <hi>whether Oxe or ſheep, the ſhoulder, the two cheeks and the maw;</hi> even ſo the Miniſters of the Goſpel, are to have from the people, as their due, not as an alms, the Goſpel maintenance, that is, thoſe endowments of the Church, being for the moſt part Tithes and Glebe given by Chriſtians to God and his Church, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the Goſpel: And the equity and juſtice of this Law, the ſame Apoſtle confirms by many more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in the ſix next precedent verſes. Firſt, From the Law of Warre, <hi>Who goeth to warfare,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>at his own charge?</hi> Secondly, From the Law of nature, <hi>Who feedeth a flock,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and eateth not of the milke? Who planteth a vineyard and eateth not of the fruit?</hi> Thirdly, From the Law of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 8, 9. <hi>Say I theſe things as a man, ſaith not the Law the ſame alſo? For it is written in the Law of Moſes, Thou ſhall not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi> And from all theſe infers this concluſion, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>If we have ſown unto you ſpirituall things, is it a great thing that we ſhall reap your carnall things?</hi> The later end of theſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Thoſe that preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ſhall live of the Goſpel,</hi> are in the Originall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and have this ſence in the judgement of very learned Interpreters, <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe that preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ſhall live of the gift or reward of the Goſpel; for which they give two reaſons: Firſt, Theſe words are an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> next before, and have this ſence, that as thoſe which wait at the Altar, ſhall partake of the gift of the Altar, ſo they that preach the glad tydings of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111508:12"/>Goſpel, ſhall live or the gift or reward due for thoſe glad tydings. Secondly, The true and proper ſignification of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> will bear it, for though in the New Teſtament it commonly ſignifies glad tydings, yet in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Greek Authours, it ſignifies a gift or reward for good tydings. That text of the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.10. as it is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in Greek by the Septuagint, leaves no place for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; where King <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks thus to <hi>Rechab</hi> and <hi>Baanah,</hi> who brought <hi>Iſhboſheths</hi> head unto him; <hi>When one told me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Behold Saul is dead (thinking to bring me good tydings) I took hold of him and ſlew him in Ziglag, who thought I would have given him a reward for his tydings,</hi> for theſe words <hi>(I would have given him a reward for his tydings)</hi> the Greek is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cui oportuit me dediſſe euangelium:</hi> The vulgar latino renders it, <hi>mercedem pro nuntio:</hi> The Chaldee Paraphraſt, <hi>Donum boni nuntij;</hi> the reward of good tydings: Many more Authours might be quoted, where that word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or glad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, is taken for a gift or reward of them, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake I ſhall omit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Tithes are due by the Law of Reaſon, from which law the Imperiall lawes which are very ſevere in the enjoyning the payment of Tithes, derive their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: to which law of Reaſon moſt Nations in the world, Pagan as well as Chriſtian, have conſented in the payment of Tithes, to men employed about the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of holy things: Eſpecially Chriſtian Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as might abundantly be ſhewed. It is true, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this laſt hundred years, ſome few Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es have taken away from the Clergy their ancient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of Tithes and Glebe, to their own uſe, and have allowed them in liew rhereof, certain yearly ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends not anſwerable to the huge fleeces they took from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111508:12"/>them, as may appear in divers Countrey dorpes or villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and elſe where, by which means the Miniſters in thoſe places are become very ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and poor, and that ignorance occaſioned by their poverty in wanting money to buy them books, and their preaching as well as their perſons deſpiſed (A contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible maintenance making a contemptible Miniſtery) This calamity learned <hi>Gualter</hi> ſaw and lamented in his time, complaining that not onely Papiſts, but ſuch, <hi>Qui Religionis ſectatores videri volunt, tamen opes eccleſiasticas, ſacrilega manu ad ſe rapiunt:</hi> even ſuch (ſaith he) as would ſeem to be profeſſors of true Reformed Religion, yet do with ſacrilegeous hands take the Church-goods to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Whence he foretells, that it will come to paſſe, <hi>ut Scholae frigeant doctiſsimi qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dilabantur:</hi> That the Schools will every where be neglected, and learned men utterly decay: Whereas here in <hi>England,</hi> by means of better maintenance of the Church, allowed to Miniſters as their own, and not dependant on the people, (agreeing to that law of reaſon I ſpake of) their perſons are more eſteemed and loved, their preaching more learned, laborious and effectuall, and the Word of God more graciouſly and fruitfully received then in any Nation in the World.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Tithes are due by the Poſitive Laws of the Land, and have been due to Church-men ever ſince Chriſtianity was planted in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe poſitive Laws derive as much from the Law of Reaſon as any Laws in the world, inſomuch that it is a maxime in the Law concerning Tythes, that they are due of Common Right, <hi>de Communi Jure,</hi> and that therefore a preſcription <hi>de non decimando,</hi> to pay no manner of Tithes, is againſt Common Right or Common Reaſon, and therefore void. This Law concerning Tithes, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111508:13"/>eſtabliſhed and confirmed by many Acts of Parliament, of which I will only name ſix: The Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 13 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. called <hi>Circumſpectè agetis,:</hi> The Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. called <hi>Articuli Cleri:</hi> The Statute of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 20.32 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 7. 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. c. 13. and the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 2. for Tithes in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus proved the Right of Tithes, I come now to the ſecond head, being the Remedy at Law for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of theſe Tithes when they are deteined.</p>
            <p>Remedy and Right do uſually go together at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law:<note place="margin">2 Head.</note> That Right which is in Law called Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe is very rare, and happens only in ſuch caſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there hath been no precedent ſeiſen or poſſeſſion, which falls not out in the caſe of Tithes, of which there hath been a conſtant ſeiſen and poſſeſſion in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> But the remedy for Tithes were anciently in the Kings temporall Courts, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>rot.</hi> 21. <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood de Fore competenti.</hi> 71. <hi>Co.</hi> 2. <hi>Instit. fol.</hi> 489, &amp;c. 18 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. (as it was by the Imperiall Laws in the Civil Courts of Emperours) ſometimes in the Sheriffs Turne, ſometimes by <hi>ſcire facias</hi> in the Chancery: And the Right of Tithes were likewiſe tried in the Kings tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Courts, as by the ancient Writts of <hi>De recto de Advocatione decimarum,</hi> and the Writt of <hi>Indicavit</hi> may appear: The firſt Statutes that annexed Tithes to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Courts (agreeing therein with the Common Law) are the Statutes of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. and <hi>Circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte agatis,</hi> made both in one year, <hi>viz.</hi> 13 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. The next Statute is 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. called <hi>Articuli Cleri:</hi> but becauſe the remedy in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts, went no further then ſpirituall cenſures, the higheſt whereof is Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, numbers of perſons cared not to hazard their ſouls ſo they might ſave their Tithes. And to this purpoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111508:13"/>is the expreſſion of the Act of Parliament of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. cap. 20. <hi>That whereas numbers of evil diſpoſed perſons, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no reſpect of their duty to Almighty God, but againſt right and good conſcience, did withhold their Tithes due to God and holy Church,</hi> as is in that Statute more at large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: By which Statute it is provided, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon refuſe to obey the Proceſſe of the Eccleſiaſticall Court for the payment of Tithes, that then upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint or information of the Ordinary, to any of the Lords of the Councel, or by two Juſtices of Peace, whereof one to be of the Quorum in the County where ſuch offender dwelleth, that then the ſaid Lord of the Councel and two Juſtices, ſhall commit ſuch offender to priſon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bayl or mainpriſe, untill he ſhall put in ſurety by. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſance to ſuch Councellour and Juſtices of Peace, to obey the Proceſſe of the Eccleſiaſticall Court.</p>
            <p>The like remedy is given by the Statute of 32 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. for a lay perſon Farmor of Tithes, by two Juſtices of Peace, after definitive ſentence in the Eccleſiaſticall Court, for the recovery of the Tithes withheld and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted againſt any perſon refuſing to obey the ſaid ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>The Statute of 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. decides the ſuit for Tithes, to be partly in the ſpirituall Court, partly in the temporall Court of the King; for perſonall Tithes, as <hi>Wool, Lamb, Flax, Hemp, Apples,</hi> &amp;c. the ſuit is only in the Eccleſiaſticall Court; but for prediall Tithes, as <hi>Corn, Grain, Hay,</hi> &amp;c. the ſuit may be either in the Kings temporall Court by action of debt for the recovery of the treble value, or in the Eccleſiaſticall Court for the double value.</p>
            <p>And this was the Law for the recovery of all Tithes whatſoever in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> till the Statutes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111508:14"/>of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. did alter the courſe of Law for Tithes of the houſes in <hi>London,</hi> which I come now to ſpeak of.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak properly: No Tithes are to be paid out of houſes; for Tithes, by the Law, are out of things that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, not out of things that diminiſh; out of things that grow, not out of things that decay: But becauſe Houſes are built upon Lands, out of which Tithes iſſued, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions were made by the owners of ſuch houſes with the Incumbent, for a yearly rent or ſumme to be paid to him, in liew of Tithes for the ground on which they were built;<note place="margin">11 Rep. D. <hi>Grants</hi> Caſe.</note> this compoſition was called, a <hi>modus decimandi,</hi> for which they ſued in <hi>London,</hi> before the Statutes of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. and 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. in the Eccleſiaſticall Court, as they did in other Cities and Burroughs thorowout <hi>England,</hi> but theſe two Statutes made an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the Law, and that the ſuit of Tithes ſhould be before the Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> &amp; in his default, before the Lord Chancellour or Keeper of <hi>England;</hi> which is the reaſon why the Statutes of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.32 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. and 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. do make ſpeciall proviſoes and exceptions of the City and Inhabitants of <hi>London,</hi> concerning their paiment of Tithes.</p>
            <p>It appears by the Statute of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. that there was much contention and ſtrife in the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and liberties of the ſame, between the Miniſters and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> concerning the paiment of Tithes, oblations and other duties within the ſaid City; for the appeaſing whereof, a certain Order and decree was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made, by <hi>Tho. Cranmer</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and <hi>Tho.</hi> Lord <hi>Audley,</hi> Lord Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> who made their Order and decree thereof about the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter, Anno Dom.</hi> 1535. which was confirmed by the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111508:14"/>Letters Patents of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and his Proclamation thereupon: Afterwards at the Parliament on the fourth of <hi>February,</hi> 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. it was then enacted; That the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and Inhabitants of the ſame City, ſhould from <hi>Eaſter</hi> next following, pay their Tithes to the Curates of the ſaid City and ſuburbs, according to the ſaid decree, untill ſuch time as any other Order or Law ſhould be made and confirmed by the Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that every perſon denying to pay his Tithes, according to the ſaid decree, ſhould by the commandment of the Lord Major for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be committed to priſon, there to remain, untill ſuch time as he ſhould have agreed with the Curate for the ſaid Tithes; as by the ſaid Statute already printed in the old Statutes at large may more appear: According to which Order and decree, the Citizens and Inhabitants of <hi>London,</hi> duely and orderly payed their Tithes to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Curates, for the ſpace of ten years together, untill the 37<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. at which time divers variances and contentions did newly ariſe between the Miniſters and Curates of the ſaid City, and the Citizens and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>London,</hi> touching the paiment of the ſaid Tithes, oblations and other duties; which ſtrife did grow, not from any unjuſtneſſe in that Order and Decree, but becauſe certain words and termes ſpecified in the ſaid Order and Decree were darke and obſcure, and not fully and plainly ſet forth, as by the Statute of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. may appear: Whereupon, as well the Paſtours, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars and Curates of <hi>London,</hi> as likewiſe the Citizens and Inhabitants of the ſame, did voluntarily of their own accord, and meerly for the appeaſing of the ſaid ſtrife then newly grown, ſubmit themſelves, to ſtand to ſuch Order and Decree upon compromiſe, touching the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111508:15"/>of Tithes, oblations and other duties within the ſaid City and liberties of <hi>London,</hi> as perſons whom they had mutually choſen for the appeaſing of the ſaid ſtrife (being the greateſt Lords and Officers of Juſtice then in the Kingdom) ſhould make and ordain; <hi>viz. Tho. Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wryothſly,</hi> Lord Chancellour of <hi>England, Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>William Pawlet,</hi> Lord S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John,</hi> Preſident of the Councell, <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Ruſſell,</hi> Lord Privy Seal, <hi>Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>Hertford,</hi> Lord great Chamberlain of <hi>England, John</hi> Vicount <hi>Liſle,</hi> high Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of <hi>England,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Richard Liſter,</hi> Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edward Mountague,</hi> Chief Juſtice of the Common Bench, and S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Roger Cholmely,</hi> Chief Juſtice of the Eſchequer; by which Statute it was enacted, that what Order ſhould be made, or decreed and concluded by the ſaid Archbiſhop, Lords and Knights, or any ſix of them, before the ſixth of <hi>March</hi> then next following, concerning the paiment of Tithes, oblations and other duties within the ſaid City and liberties of the ſame, and enrolled in the Kings high Court of Chancery of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſhould be as an Act of Parliament, and ſhould binde all Citizens and Inhabitants of <hi>London,</hi> and all Vicars, Parſons and Curates of the ſaid City, and their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours for ever: And that every perſon denying to pay Tithes or other duties, contrary to the ſaid Decree ſo to be made and enrolled, ſhould by the commandment of the Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> and in his default, by the Lord Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> be committed to priſon, there to remain, till ſuch time as he or they ſhould have agreed with the Curate or Curates for his or their Tithes, as by the ſaid Statute may more appear, eight of which ten perſons made their Decree accordingly, the 24. day of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111508:15"/>
               <hi>February,</hi> in the year 1545. (<hi>Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edward Moumague</hi> were only left out) which De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree I affirme to be enrolled in the Court of Chancery, and a true Copy of that enrolled Decree, is at this day printed with the Statute of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. And I make no doubt, but the City of <hi>London</hi> hath likewiſe an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification of that inrolled Decree under the broad Seal: And though M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Claydon,</hi> by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Norburies</hi> direction, ſearching in the Chappel of the Rolls could not finde it, doth it follow therefore, that an other Clerke cannot finde it? Or if it cannot at this day be found, doth it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the negative, that never any ſuch Decree was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled? How many printed Statutes have we at this day, by which the Judges of the Realm do adjudge caſes in Law, of which the originall Records cannot at this day be found? and the like hath been of this printed Decree for theſe hundred years, without reference to the Record in Chancery.</p>
            <p>But admitting there was never at all any ſuch enrolled Decree, will it therefore follow, or will any Lawyer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that then there is no remedy for Tythes in <hi>London?</hi> doth not the former Decree of Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and the Lord Chancellour <hi>Audley</hi> then take place? For that Decree is not repealed by the Statute of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. by any words in that Law, but was to continue in force, till the Decree upon arbitrement and compromiſe was made; if this later was never made, then that former Decree con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues ſtill; and if that former Decree was extinct and gone, to which the Proviſoes in the Statutes of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and 32 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. do only refer, then Tithes in <hi>London,</hi> are due and paiable as formerly by the Eccleſiaſticall Law, ſo that <hi>quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> via data,</hi> there is a ready and certain remedy for the recovery of the Tithes of Houſes in <hi>London:</hi> So weak
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111508:16"/>and feeble are thoſe weapons which are lifted up againſt the force &amp; ſtrength of truth, which I hope I have cleerly layed open in the point of Tithes, both for the Right and for the Remedy, even to the Pamphleters themſelves, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they will <hi>caecutire ante ſolem,</hi> as the Proverb is. And therefore they begin to ſhift their weapons, and in ſtead of arguments againſt the Statute of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and the Decree of Tithes upon it, they ſlander down-right that very Parliament of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. I abhor to do them the leaſt wrong, and therefore I will quote the very words of one of their champion Pamphlets, like another <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> called <hi>The Inditement of Tithes.</hi> By the many ſcandals and errours but of one paſſage in that book, you may eaſily judge what to thinke of the truth of all the reſt contained in that Pamphlet. The words to the Lord Major, among other reaſons and grounds againſt Tithes, are theſe; <hi>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip to take into conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, what an over-ruling hand King</hi> Henry <hi>the eighth and his Privy Councel did bear over the Parliament at that time, which as it appeared in other things, ſo eſpecially in this of Tithes, in</hi> Anno 37 <hi>of his reign, prevailing ſo far, as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce that Parliament to delegate their power in a matter of ſo great concernment to the then Archbiſhop and other Lords and Knights, Enacting that whatſoever they ſhould decree therein, ſhould binde at the Citizens for ever: an unheard of ſtrain of Parliament, to confirm (with reverence we ſpeak it) they know not what, and which to this day hath had no other confirmation: In which Decree, we pray your Lordſhip to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ignorance and ſuperſtition of that age, that followed the ſteps of their erroneous predeceſsours, both in Epiſcopacy and Tithes, without comparing them to the word of God; alſo the unequall dealing of thoſe entruſted, providing that great mens dwelling houſes ſhould be free from Tithes; whereby it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111508:16"/>may appear, this Decree or Law for Tithes (if it deſerve to be ſo called) is not ſo valid or reaſonable as it is generally concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and however ought not to be pleaded or stand in force, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the word and minde of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In which words you may obſerve theſe ſcandals and untruths: Firſt, Where the Lord Major is deſired to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <hi>what an over-ruling hand King</hi> Henry <hi>the eighth and his Privy Councel did bear over the Parliament at that time, which as it appeareth in other things, ſo eſpecially in this of Tithes, in</hi> Anno 37 <hi>of his reigne,</hi> &amp;c. There are no leſſe then theſe three ſlanders. Firſt, of the perſon of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, who did nothing in this buſineſſe of Tithes, but as a tender father to the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> who loved him and he them, not as an overbearing Prince; for it appears plainly by that Statute, that it was an Act of grace in him; the words are theſe; <hi>To the intent to have a full peace and perfect end between the ſaid parties, their heirs and ſucceſſours touching the ſaid Tithes, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and other duties for ever; Be it Enacted,</hi> &amp;c. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of his actions, making him in this matter of Tithes, and in other things to be unjuſt, not naming the things; which in that thoſe things not named, are referred to the buſineſſe of Tithes, wherein he did no wrong, it increaſes the ſlander. Thirdly, of his Privy Councel, who as appeareth plainly by the Act, were only uſed as refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rees and arbitratours choſen by the Paſtours, Vicars, Curates, and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> for the ending of the ſtrife amongſt them concerning Tithes, and made their Decree accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Where it is ſaid by the Inditour, that King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth and his Privy Councel, prevailed <hi>ſo far as to induce that Parliament to delegate their power in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great concernment, to the then Archbiſhop and other
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111508:17"/>Lords And Knights, Enacting, that whatſoever they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree therein, ſhould binde all the Citizens for ever; an unheard of strain of Parliament, to confirm (with reverence we ſpeak it) they knew not what, and which to this day hath had no other confirmation.</hi> In which words theſe ſcandals and untruths are to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, There is a groſſe ſcandall upon that Parliament, and upon all Parliaments in generall, as to charge them with a delegation of their power to a few, a thing againſt the Honour and dignity of a Parliament, to transfer that High power with which the Law hath intruſted them to a few, as may appear by the Parliament Roll of 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 70. which very thing by the printed Statute of 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. chiefly occaſioned the repeal of the whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of 21 <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. And what a ſtrange unlimited pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that Parliament committed to a few perſons, may more particularly appear by the Statute of 21 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. in the old printed Statutes at large, to which I wholly remit the Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, It is not only a ſcandall, but a notorious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, to charge that Parliament that they Enacted and confirmed they knew not what. For</p>
            <p>Firſt it appears plainly by that Statute, that the matter was only concerning Tithes, oblations and other duties within the City and ſuburbs of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Names of thoſe Lords and Knights, to whom the differences concerning thoſe things were refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, are particularly mentioned in that Statute, and their perſons particularly known to that Parliament.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it appears by that Statute, That the Miniſters and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> did voluntarily ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the differences between them concerning Tithes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the decree and arbitrament of thoſe perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:111508:17"/>Fourthly, that thoſe Arbitratours are limited and tied up to a former Order of the Lord Chancellour <hi>Audley,</hi> and the Statute of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. upon it, concerning the Tithes of <hi>London,</hi> for it appears plainly in the Statute of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. that the differences about Tithes, did not ariſe from any matter touching the ſubſtance of that former Order, but from certain ambiguous words, and obſcure termes in it not plainly ſet forth, whereby it is evident and cleer, that that Parliament did particularly know what it did, but the Inditour did not, when he laid ſo foul and falſe a charge upon that Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, where the Lord Major is deſired to obſerve in the Decree, <hi>The ignorance and ſuperstition of that age, that followed the ſteps of their erroneous predeceſsours, both in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy and Tithes, without comparing thins with the word of God:</hi> Therein there is a double ſlander;</p>
            <p>Firſt, of that whole age, that in the buſineſſ of Tithes did nothing according to the word of God: when as it appears plainly by the Statute of 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 20. That that Parliament, being the beſt repreſentation of that age, did compare Tithes with the word of God, and the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paiment of them, to be firſt, a deteſtable enormity, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, againſt right and a good conſcience, thirdly, againſt mens duty to Almighty God, as may more appear by that Statute.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is a particular ſlander of the then Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (for there was no other Biſhop mentioned in that Decree,) as if he followed the ſteps of his erroneous predeceſſours in ignorance and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when for that very cauſe he was perſecuted to death, by only ſuch kinde of Biſhops whoſe ſteps he is ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to follow; a man ſo holy, that even M. <hi>Brightman</hi> himſelf (no friend to Biſhops) doth make him to be that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111508:18"/>Angel in the fourteenth Chapter of the <hi>Revelations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeos.</note> that in the meaning of the holy Ghoſt, had power over the fire. And whereas he is ſuppoſed by the Inditour, to follow the ignorance and ſuperſtition of that age, as not to compare things with the word of God, I have ſeen a Treatiſe of his againſt <hi>Stephen Gardener</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> wherein lie profeſſeth that the word of God was the Rule that guided him in the Reformation of Religion, wherein he had a chief ſtroak, both in the dayes of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly and laſtly, whereas the Lord Major is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to obſerve <hi>the unequall dealing of thoſe entruſted, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding that Great mens dwelling houſes ſhould be free from Tithes.</hi> It is as great an untruth as it is a groſſe ſlander; for the words of the Statute are theſe; <hi>Provided always, that this Decree ſhall not extend to the houſes of Great men, or Noble men, or Noble women kept in their own hands, and not letten for any rent, which in times past have paid no Tithes, ſo long as they ſhall ſo continue unletten.</hi> Which proviſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conſtruction of the whole Decree, doth belong to all other men who had never letten their houſes to farme, but kept them ſtill in their hands, as was reſolved by all the Judges of the Common Pleas,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>2.</hi> part. Inſt it <hi>p.</hi> 6, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Mich</hi> 5 <hi>Jac.</hi> in a Caſe between <hi>John Scudamore</hi> and <hi>Robert Eyre</hi> in a Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt <hi>John Bell,</hi> and ſo hath that Decree ever been conſtrued and taken: ſo that there was no ſelf-reſpect, injuſtice or partiality at all in the Commiſſioners which made that Proviſo in the Decree, as is untruly caſt upon them by that Inditour.</p>
            <p>The reſt of all that Pamphlet is of no better ſtuff, but may wholly be reduced to theſe three-heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Manifeſt abuſe and miſinterprerations of the ſacred Scriptures, common to all Sectaries and Innovatours.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:111508:18"/>2. Notorious miſ-quotations and miſunderſtanding of Authours, as of M. <hi>Selden, ſo. Huſſe, Pierce Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>John Oldcaſtle,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>3. Groſſe railing and reviling of mens perſons, as namely of M. <hi>Thomas Clendon,</hi> by the name of <hi>Prieſt Clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which he puts upon him as a terme of ſcorn, though <hi>revera,</hi> and in truth it be a name of Honour, for Prieſt is nothing elſe but an old engliſh contraction of <hi>Preſter</hi> in French, of <hi>Presbyter</hi> in Latine, and of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Greek, ſignifying <hi>Elder</hi> in our engliſh tongue, and is the very ſame Honourable name given to the four and twenty Elders,<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v. 4 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> mentioned in the fourth and fifth Chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> which are there deſcribed to ſit about the Throne of Chriſt, <hi>clothed in white raiment, with crowns of gold on their heads, and golden viols in their hands full of odours, which are the prayers of the Saints.</hi> And beſides this ſcorn, to render him more odious to the people (which is the ſtudied deſigne againſt many good men at this day) he is reported by the Pamphleter, to be a conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious man, a ſower of ſtrife and debate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as great an oppoſite as can be to a godly Miniſter of the Goſpel (as I hear he is) being alſo a man of whom I cannot eaſily be induced to thinke any ill, having his education from godly parents and a religious School-maſter, and under as Orthodox, pious and powerfull a Miniſtery, as was (at that time I knew him) in <hi>Northampton</hi>-ſhire.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And thus have I, as briefly as I could, vindicated the lawfullneſſe of Tithes, and the paiment of them to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters under the Goſpel, ſufficient I hope to ſatisfie any reaſonable man that makes godlineſſe his gain, not gain his godlineſſe: eſpecially ſuch gain as taken from the Church and Church-men, will prove to the poſſeſſours of them, like <hi>aurumTholoſanum,</hi> the gold of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:111508:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:111508:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:111508:20"/>which beggered all thoſe men and their families that had any of it;<note place="margin">Numb. 5.</note> or like the <hi>bitter and curſed water</hi> to the guilty woman, which cauſed <hi>her belly to ſwell,</hi> but <hi>her thigh to rot;</hi> a very emphaticall and ſignificant expreſſion, noting a ſucceſſive curſe upon poſterity, <hi>thigh,</hi> intimating ſo much in a Scripture phraſe; as to give one inſtance for all, <hi>Gen.</hi> 46. <hi>v.</hi> 26. where it is ſaid, that all the poſterity of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> that came with him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> came out of his <hi>thigh;</hi> even ſo, though the revenews of the Church ſhall cauſe a ſwelling in their eſtates at the firſt, yet it will bring upon them, their poſterity and eſtates, a rot and conſumption at the laſt, according to that experimentall ſaying of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great,<note place="margin">In Cap. <hi>Carul.</hi> lib. 2. c. 104.</note> 
               <hi>Novimus multa Regna &amp; Reges eorum propterea cecidiſſe, quia Eccleſias ſpoliaverunt, reſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eorum vaſtaverunt;</hi> we have known (ſaith he) many Kingdoms with their Kings brought to ruin, becauſe they ſpoiled Churches, and made a prey of their revenews.</p>
            <p>Much more might be ſaid in confirmation of ſo well approved, and ſo ancient a truth as the Right of Tithes, which I do for the preſent purpoſely forbear, for that I am loth to call into queſtion ſo ſolid, ſo ſetled and ſo well principled a verity, in ſo vain, ſo fickle, and ſo unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed an age, which at this day brings into diſpute the moſt fixed Principles that are: a thing ſo abhorring to <hi>Aristotle</hi> (though but a Heathen,) that he would have ſuch kinde of contentions to receive confutation, <hi>verberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non verbis, baculis non argumentis.</hi> Beſides, the eager conteſtation about Tithes, falls out at this day amongſt ſuch kinde of men as are not ſo converſant with learning and reaſon, as with ignorance and clamour, of whom <hi>Tacitus</hi> gives this character, which I will leave for others to engliſh, <hi>plebi non judicium, non veritas, ex opinione multa, ex veritate pauca judicat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111508:20"/>I ſhall only for concluſion, deſire theſe men to lay aſide that gall of bitterneſſe with which they have hitherto overabounded, as incompetible with that ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is required in true Chriſtians; to ſuſpect al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies that truth which is not accompanied with peace: thoſe men that have bitter envying and ſtrife in their hearts, are in the judgement of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">James 3.14.</note> lyars againſt truth, ſo that to ſtrive againſt peace, is to lye againſt truth; to conſider the infinite poverty and confuſion that would be in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if it ſhould be quite ſtript of its ancient endowments: and laſtly to remember the example of the Emperour <hi>Julian,</hi> who in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his reign, gloried in nothing more then in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtian religion, in ſo much as he became a publike reader of holy Scriptures in the Church, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fell into apoſtaſie, till he fell to Church-robbing; whereby his perſecution of Chriſtians was accounted far greater then that of <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> who though he put far more Miniſters to death then ever <hi>Julian,</hi> yet he did not <hi>occidere presbyterium,</hi> he ſlew not the Prieſthood, is <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> did, by depriving the Church and Church-men of their maintenance; whereupon in the opinion of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret,</hi> after he had robbed the Churches of all their plate, and in a ſcoffing manner asked, <hi>whether thoſe were ſit veſſels for a Carpenters ſon to be ſerved with,</hi> God wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſuddenly to death with an arrow ſhot from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: <hi>exemplum audiſti, cave ſupplicium,</hi> I have told them the example, let them take heed of the puniſhment.</p>
            <p>I began this diſcourſe with the Law of the Land, I will conclude it with the Law of the Goſpel, being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, mentioned in the Goſpel of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Matthew,</hi> cap. 7. v. 12. being the words of our Saviour in his Sermon on the mount, <hi>whatſoever ye
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111508:21"/>would that men ſhould do to you, even ſo do ye to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> The people of <hi>England</hi> would think themſelves much wronged, if Miniſters ſhould preach againſt their property of goods: and is not the ſame wrong offered to Miniſters, when the people ſpeak and write againſt their patrimony of Tithes? the ſame <hi>Magna Charta</hi> that confirms the one, eſtabliſhes the other. <hi>Do is ye would he done by,</hi> is the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: <hi>Render to every man his due,</hi> is the Law of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: <hi>Quod tibi ſieri non vis, alteri ne feceris,</hi> is the Law of Nature and Nations; <hi>triplici nodo triplex cuneus,</hi> and ſuch a three fold cord is not eaſily broken; if it ſhould, I tremble to thinke of the miſery and ruin that will fall out to a people or Nation at ſuch a breach. The Lord make us all wiſe and juſt, in an age ſo wilfull and wicked.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111508:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
